Finding Aid for Sherwin T. Wine papers, 1930s-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sherwin T. Wine papers
1930s-2011
Wine, Sherwin T.
045 Aa 2 UAm
Sherwin T. Wine was the iconoclastic founder of Humanistic Judaism and an openly gay rabbi who established the Birmingham Temple and formed the Society for Humanistic Judaism, the Center for New Thinking (a community forum for discussion of current events and issues), and various groups devoted to free thought and humanism. Papers include biographical content, correspondence, writings, educational and worship materials, sound recordings, visual materials, and various organizational records.
36.5 linear feet in 42 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The first accession was received from Sherwin T. Wine (donor no. 9404 ) in December 2003; additional materials were received from the International Institute for Secular Humanistic Judaism (donor no. 10153 ) in 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Rabbi Sherwin T. Wine was born in Detroit, Michigan on January 25, 1928 to Polish immigrant parents (Tieblei, or "Tillie," and Herschel, who changed the family name from Wengrowski upon his arrival in America). The public schools he attended in Detroit had largely Jewish student bodies and he was raised in an environment of Conservative Judaism, with a kosher home and regular observance of Shabbat. He attended the University of Michigan where he became interested in empirical philosophy as well as the humanistic outlook of some professors. After earning a B.A. and M.A. in philosophy, Wine decided to join the clergy rather than pursue a Ph.D and he enrolled in Reform Judaism's Hebrew Union College in 1951.
Following his ordination, Wine volunteered for the U.S. Army as a chaplain and he served briefly as an assistant rabbi at Detroit's Temple Beth El prior to his induction. Deployed to Korea in January 1957, Wine returned to Detroit in November 1958 and resumed his duties at Beth El. He remained there until 1959 at which point he founded a Reform congregation in Windsor, Ontario. While he had always been skeptical of orthodox religion, it was during this time that Wine's philosophic doubts about the nature of God grew stronger. When a sympathetic group of eight families from suburban Detroit approached him in 1963 with the idea of forming a new congregation, he jumped at the opportunity.
The Birmingham Temple was established in 1963 and held its first service at an elementary school on September 15, 1963. Wine's approach to Judaism de-emphasized the significance of a higher power, and instead extolled Jewish history and culture and promoted humanistic values. To express more accurately the true beliefs of his congregation, Wine eliminated the word "God" from his services so that a phrase such as "You shall love the Lord your God," became instead "We revere the best in man." This stance helped lay the foundations for Humanistic Judaism as a distinct alternative to other established denominations within the Jewish faith (Orthodox, Conservative, Reform, and Reconstructionist). At a basic level, Humanistic Judaism was based upon the belief that humans may achieve meaningful lives within themselves and have the power and responsibility for their own lives and actions without divine intervention.
These bold innovations courted controversy; by 1965, coverage in the Detroit Free Press, Time, and the New York Times had publicized the Birmingham Temple's exclusion of God from their service. Wine was asked to recant or leave the Jewish tradition, and the Council of Orthodox Rabbis in Detroit publicly denounced Humanistic Judaism. The congregation was expelled from the Masonic temple where they had begun to meet and the temple eventually relocated to Farmington Hills where a newly built facility opened in 1971. Despite these challenges, Wine's message found an increasingly receptive audience: the Birmingham Temple grew to 140 families by 1965 and over 400 by the time of his death in 2007. As of 2009, Humanistic Judaism has over 50,000 followers worldwide in more than 100 congregations.
Wine devoted his life to the advancement of Humanistic Judaism; in a personal statement from the 1990s, he wrote "Throughout the years of my work as a Jewish educator, my motivation has remained the same--to create the educational framework for a viable Secular Humanistic Judaism." In 1969, the Birmingham Temple and likeminded congregations in Illinois and Connecticut formed the Society for Humanistic Judaism to better promote the religion throughout the United States and develop educational and programmatic materials. The movement would later expand its reach with the 1986 creation of the International Federation of Secular Humanistic Jews (IFSHJ), for which Wine served as the founding chair. While the IFSHJ would serve as the global expression of the faith, Wine had already begun to strengthen the foundations of Humanistic Judaism the previous year (1985) with the inauguration of the International Institute for Secular Humanistic Judaism (IISHJ) in Jerusalem. Wine, who served as the Dean and Provost of the IISHJ's North American branch (which would be located at the Ben and Lorraine Pivnick Center for Humanistic Judaism in Farmington Hills, MI), envisioned the Institute as the intellectual and educational arm of the IFSHJ. From its inception, the IISHJ's primary purposes were to commission and publish materials for the movement and to train rabbis, leaders, teachers, educators and spokespersons. This second goal was realized more fully with its initiation of a Rabbinic Program for the training of Humanistic rabbis in 1991; the curriculum includes Institute studies with the acquisition of a PhD in Judaic Studies from a secular university. Although he had retired from the Birmingham Temple in 2003, Wine remained active in the movement until his untimely death in 2007.
Beyond his work as a rabbi and founder of Humanistic Judaism, Wine was a passionate advocate for humanist values in general. In 1976, he established the Center for New Thinking as a community forum for emerging thinking in religion, politics, arts, sciences, and philosophy. Wine's lectures, forums, and seminars examined literature, notable biographies, and current and historical events to help his audiences better understand the world and confront the challenges of everyday life. Although Wine served as director and chief lecturer of the Center until his death, he would become involved with a variety of other groups. Dismayed by the rise of right-wing fundamentalism in the early 1980s, he helped found the Voice of Reason (it would merge with the Center for Moral Democracy in 1982 and become known as Americans for Religious Liberty) to advocate for the separation of church and state. Wine was also responsible for the formation of the North American Committee for Humanism (NACH) and its affiliated Humanist Institute in 1982. Wine served as the president of the NACH, a confederation of the six major humanist organizations in North America, as well as its Institute, a graduate school in New York City that trains humanist leaders, until 1993. In addition, Wine founded the Conference on Liberal Religion (an association of liberal religious professionals) in 1985 and an advocacy group called Clergy and Citizens United in 1995 and served on the board of the Triangle Foundation and the Arts Foundation of Michigan. To recognize his lifelong contributions, the American Humanist Association named Wine Humanist of the Year in 2003. Past recipients of the award, which was established in 1953 to recognize individuals who have made "a significant contribution to the improvement of the human condition," include Betty Friedan, Carl Sagan, Stephen Jay Gould, Kurt Vonnegut, Margaret Sanger, and Jonas Salk. More recently, Wine continued to lecture frequently in the Detroit area and in 2007 helped found the advocacy group Scientists and Citizens United to counter reactionary responses to issues such as stem cell research. Sherwin T. Wine died in a car accident on July 21, 2007 while on vacation in Essaouira, Morocco with his longtime life partner Richard McMains.
The Sherwin T. Wine papers illustrate the intellectual traits and organizational acumen of a man who devoted his life to the establishment of a new branch of Judaism and the advancement of humanistic values and rationalism. The collection will be of value to those individuals who seek a deeper understanding of Wine as a person as well as the founder of Humanistic Judaism. Writings, correspondence, and clippings detail the process by which Wine broke free from the traditions of Reform Judaism to found a new denomination. Materials from the Birmingham Temple and other Secular Humanist Judaism organizations trace the development and expansion of the movement. Content related to the many other groups with which Wine was involved reveal an individual able to organize and inspire others to act at local, national, and international levels.
Subjects:
Wine, Sherwin T.; Americans for Religious Liberty.; Arts Foundation of Michigan.; Birmingham Temple (Farmington Hills, Mich.); Center for New Thinking.; Clergy and Citizens United.; Humanistic Judaism.; International Federation of Secular Humanistic Jews.; International Institute for Secular Humanistic Judaism.; Jews--Michigan.; North American Committee for Humanism.; Society for Humanistic Judaism.; Rabbis--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Wine, Sherwin T.; Humanistic Judaism.; Birmingham Temple (Farmington Hills, Mich.); Center for New Thinking.; Jews--Michigan.; Rabbis--Michigan.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Center for New Thinking.; Humanistic Judaism.; Wine, Sherwin T.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; DVDs.; Oral histories.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical series contains material relating to Wine's academic, professional, and personal lives. Content includes academic files from Wine's studies in philosophy and theology at the University of Michigan and Hebrew Union College; daily agendas from the 1970s and 1980s; and clippings related to Wine's career as well as the growth of the Birmingham Temple and other associated organizations. The series also encompasses personal tributes to Wine from members of this congregation, eulogies and funeral materials, and background information on Wine and his family (including his sister and brother-in-law, Lorraine and Ben Pivnick, major benefactors of the Humanistic Judaism movement).
  - Academic Files
    - Aesthetics, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Aramaic, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Aristotle, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - The Bible, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Christian Philosophy, 1950s-1960 (Box 1)
    - Economics, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - English Constitution, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Epistemology, 1948-1960 (Box 1)
    - Ethics, 1940s-1965 (Box 1)
    - European Government, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 1)
    - Fascism, 1943 (Box 1)
    - Gibbons, Edward, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Essay submitted to the Hopwood Contest for Freshmen)
    - Grammar, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Hamilton, Alexander, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - History of Religion, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Hume, David, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - International Law, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Kant, Immanuel, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Linguistic Analysis, 1952-1962 (Box 1)
    - Logic, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Metaphysics, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1)
    - Mathematics, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Midrash, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Near East, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - Political Science, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Politics, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Proudhon, Pierre Joseph, circa 1940s (Box 1)
    - Rilke, Rainier Maria, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Royal Genealogies, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Semantics, circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Socrates, circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - State Government, circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Talmud, circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Theology, circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Treaties, 1942-1951 (Box 2)
    - Value Theory, circa 1950s (Box 2)
  - Awards and Recognition
    - American Humanist Association (AHA) Humanist of the Year Award, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Various, 1980s-2000s (Box 2)
  - Background, undated, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Birthday Celebrations, 1988-1998 (Box 2)
  - Clippings
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1946 (Box 2)
    - 1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - 1986-1988 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995-1998 (Box 2)
    - 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 2)
    - 2003 (Box 2)
    - 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 2)
    - 2008 (Box 2)
    - 2002-2007 (Box 41)
      (oversize)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 2000s (Box 2)
  - Daily Agenda
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
    - 1977 (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984 (Box 2)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1989 (Box 3)
  - Diploma (Hebrew Union College), 1956; facsimile (Box 3)
  - Festschrift, undated (Box 42)
    (includes photo)
  - Memorial Services and Eulogies for Sherwin T. Wine, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Pivnick, Ben and Lorraine (sister of Sherwin T. Wine), 1963-1998 (Box 3)
  - Statements of Purpose and Motivation, undated (Box 3)
  - Tributes to Sherwin T. Wine, undated (Box 3)
  - Travel, 1985-2007 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is arranged chronologically and contains letters written to and by Wine as well as a selection of the many greeting cards sent to Wine by friends and admirers. The correspondence covers a variety of topics: questions about the Birmingham Temple and its practices and beliefs; moral support and congratulations for Rabbi Wine; planning for the temple and its publications; requests for speaking engagements; and Wine's involvement in a range of organizations.
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Draft Letter to Humanistic Reform Rabbis, circa 1960s (Box 3)
  - 1962 (Box 3)
  - 1963 (Box 3)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - 1966 (Box 3)
  - 1968-1979 (Box 3)
  - 1981 (Box 3)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
  - 1984 (Box 3)
  - 1985 (Box 3)
  - 1986 (Box 3)
  - 1987 (Box 3)
  - 1988 (Box 3)
  - 1989 (Box 3)
  - 1990 (Box 3)
  - 1991 (Box 3)
  - 1992 (Box 3)
  - 1993 (Box 3)
  - 1994 (Box 3)
  - 1995 (Box 3)
  - 1996 (Box 3)
  - 1997 (Box 3)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2000 (Box 3)
  - 2001 (Box 3)
  - 2002 (Box 3)
  - 2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 2004 (Box 4)
  - 2005 (Box 4)
  - 2006 (Box 4)
  - 2007 (Box 4)
  - Greeting Cards, 1980s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Writings
  The Writings series contains articles, books, essays, manuscripts and other materials as well as related content (reviews, publicity, page proofs, and some royalty statements). By and large, these works deal with questions of faith, Jewish culture, the nature of a meaningful existence, and the creation and practice of Humanistic Judaism. Many of the essays appear to have been used as the basis for lectures, but exact dates and venues are not known. Wine's publications include the books Humanistic Judaism; Judaism Beyond God; Celebration; High Holidays for Humanists; and Staying Sane in a Crazy World as well as contributions to collections such as Judaism in a Secular Age: An Anthology of Secular Humanistic Jewish Thought and Radical Theologians in Conversation. His articles appeared in a variety of journals, including Humanistic Judaism, Free Inquiry, The Humanist, and American Rationalist. The series furthermore includes an extensive collection of "The Rabbi Writes," Wine's regular column from the Birmingham Temple's newsletter (The Jewish Humanist). The series also contains A Life of Courage: Sherwin Wine and Humanistic Judaism (compiled by Dan Cohn-Sherbok, Harry T. Cook, and Marilyn Rowens), a volume that honors Wine's contributions to the movement and presents his personal assessment of his life's work.
  Parts of some titles in this series are stored on digital media: Jews without Abraham, Moses or God (CD-ROM), Jews: A Provocative People (three 3.5" floppy disks and one USB drive), Tough Minds-Tender Hearts (two 3.5" disks).
  - Articles
    - Humanism Today, 1986 (Box 4)
    - The Humanist, 1998-2002 (Box 4)
    - Humanistic Judaism, 1974-2000s (Box 4)
    - International Humanist, 1987 (Box 4)
    - The Jewish News, 1990s (Box 4)
    - "The Rabbi Writes" (Jewish Humanist), 1970s-2000s; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Religious Humanism, 1967-1979 (Box 4)
    - Various Sources, 1970s-2003 (Box 4)
  - Books
    - Celebration, 2003 (Box 4)
    - Judaism Beyond God, 1995 (Box 4)
    - Judaism in a Secular Age, 1995 (Box 5)
    - A Life of Courage, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Staying Sane in a Crazy World, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Essays
    - Anti-Semitism, undated (Box 5)
    - "Demystifying Family Values", circa 1990s (Box 5)
    - Ethics, undated (Box 5)
    - Holocaust, undated (Box 5)
    - Humanism as Religion, undated, 1982-2003 (Box 5)
    - Humanistic Judaism, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
    - Humanistic Judaism and Politics, undated (Box 5)
    - Humanistic Judaism and Tradition, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
    - International Jewry, 1973-2000s (Box 5)
    - Israel, 1970-2000s (Box 5)
    - Muslim World, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 5)
    - Various, undated (Box 5)
  - Manuscripts and Related Materials
    - Celebration
      - Outline, undated (Box 5)
      - Page Proofs, circa 1990 (Box 5)
      - Reviews and Publicity, 1990 (Box 5)
      - Songs, 1988-1989; undated (Box 5)
    - History (book?), untitled, undated (Box 42)
    - Humanistic Judaism, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Humanistic Judaism: an Anthology, 1986 (Box 5)
    - Jews: A Provocative People, 2000s; 3 folders; 3 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 6)
      (includes three 3.5" floppy disks)
      (see also Real History of the Jews)
    - Judaism Beyond God
      - Reviews, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
      - Russian Translation, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Judaism in a Secular Age, circa 1990s (Box 6)
    - A Life of Courage, 2001-2003 (Box 6)
    - Living with the Enemy, circa 2000s (Box 6)
    - Radical Theologians in Conversation, 1999 (Box 6)
      (Contribution by Wine to an anthology)
    - Real History of the Jews
      (see also Jews: A Provocative People)
      - 1997, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Related files (Box 42)
        - 2007 (Box 42)
          (USB drive)
        - Manuscript, Undated (Box 42)
        - Vol. 1 edits, 2011 (Box 42)
          (CD-R)
    - Staying Sane in a Crazy World
      - Book Proposal, circa 1990s (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, Reviews, and Publicity, 1995-2006 (Box 6)
      - Original Handwritten Draft, circa 1990s (Box 6)
      - Proposed Cover Art, circa 1995 (Box 6)
      - Spanish Translation, 1998-2000 (Box 6)
  - Other (includes contributions by Wine to various projects)
    - Book Reviews, undated, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Encyclopedia of Contemporary American Religion, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 7)
    - Creative Works, undated (Box 7)
    - "A Dialogue on Unitarianism and Humanism", 1979-1980 (Box 7)
    - Encyclopedia of Unbelief, 2004-2006 (Box 7)
    - Fountain Street Church Sermons, 1986-1991 (Box 7)
    - Jews without Abraham, Moses or God, 2006-2007 (Box 7)
      (includes CD-R)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 7)
    - Royalty Statements, 1999-2003 (Box 7)
    - Tape Transcriptions, 1980s (Box 7)
    - Tough Minds-Tender Hearts, unpublished, 1988; 2 floppy disks 3.5" (Box 7)
      (includes two 3.5" floppy disks)
    - What Israel Means to Me, 2004 (Box 7)
- Humanistic Judaism
  The Humanistic Judaism series is divided into two subseries: Educational Materials and Services, Ceremonies and Holidays (the latter of which includes content produced by the Birmingham Temple). Taken as a whole, these papers outline the philosophies and practices that underlie Humanistic Judaism as a faith.
  - Educational Materials
    The Educational Materials subseries provides an overview of the movement's roots within Judaism and humanistic thought and includes introductory course materials, relevant readings, and various writings by Wine.
    - Basic Principles of Humanistic Judaism, circa 2000s (Box 7)
    - A Book of Quotations, undated (Box 7)
    - Dietary Laws, undated (Box 7)
    - Glossary of Humanistic Judaism Terms (A-M), circa 1990s (Box 7)
    - History of Humanistic Judaism, 1969-1980s (Box 7)
    - History of Judaism, undated (Box 7)
    - Humanist Manifestos I-III, 1973-1999 (Box 7)
    - Humanistic Philosophers, undated (Box 7)
    - Introductory Guides to Humanistic Judaism, undated (Box 7)
    - "The New Mysticism and The Power of Myth", undated (Box 7)
    - Public Response to Humanistic Judaism, 1965-1980 (Box 7)
    - Reading Lists, undated (Box 7)
    - Relevant Readings, undated (Box 7)
    - Roots of Secular Humanistic Judaism, undated (Box 7)
    - "A Secular Humanist Declaration", undated (Box 7)
    - "Skills for Living in a Humanistic Jewish Community", undated (Box 7)
    - "Trailblazers of Humanistic Judaism", undated (Box 7)
  - Services, Ceremonies, and Holidays (includes materials related to the Birmingham Temple)
    The Services, Ceremonies, and Holidays subseries, on the other hand, illustrates how Humanistic Judaism has adapted traditional Jewish holidays and rituals to become a unique denomination. Content includes Wine's writings on Humanistic Judaism's adaptation of traditional rituals and observations, programs from worship services at the Birmingham Temple and elsewhere, and related materials. These papers include a large number of songs and music appropriate for use in humanistic temples.
    - Adoption/Conversion, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 7)
    - Adult Confirmation, circa 1990s (Box 7)
    - America Day, undated (Box 7)
    - Birth Ceremonies, circa 1990s (Box 7)
    - Circumcision, 1969-1988 (Box 7)
    - Funerals, circa 1980s (Box 7)
    - Hanukkah, circa 1990s (Box 7)
    - Havdala Services, undated (Box 7)
    - High Holidays, circa 1990s (Box 7)
    - Holiday Stories, undated (Box 7)
    - Humanistic History of the High Holidays, undated (Box 7)
    - Israel Day and Tu Bi-Shevat, 1979-1998 (Box 7)
    - Leadership Day, undated (Box 7)
    - Life Cycle, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Marriage, circa 1960s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Meditation Services, 1945-2000s (Box 7)
    - Memorial Services, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 7)
    - Mitsva and Confirmation, circa 1980s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Naming, 1960s-1990s (Box 8)
    - New Year's Day, undated (Box 8)
    - Passover, 1970s-2000s (Box 8)
    - People Day/Humanism Day, 1982-1999 (Box 8)
    - Poetic Services, undated (Box 8)
    - Purim, 1992-2006 (Box 8)
    - Remembrance/Holocaust Day, 1985-2000 (Box 8)
    - Rosh Hashanah, 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Shabbat, circa 1990s-2000s; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Shavuot, 1980-1996 (Box 8)
    - Songs
      - circa 1980s-1990s (Box 8)
      - 1988 (Box 8)
    - Sukkot, 1980s-2000 (Box 8)
    - Temple Day, 1965-1988, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Thanksgiving, 1960s-1990s (Box 8)
    - World Day, 1978-1995 (Box 9)
    - Yom Kippur, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 9)
- Birmingham Temple
  The Birmingham Temple series contains materials related to the temple's operation as well as Wine's rabbinical duties. Content includes temple events (anniversaries, Monday Forums, etc.), administrative files, correspondence (to and from Wine), adult and youth education materials, newsletters, press releases and clippings, and a large collection of programs from temple services. Files related to Wine's rabbinical duties contain sermons (a large portion of which date from the 1960s), marriage records, and various special events.
  - Activities
    - Anniversaries
      - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Thirtieth Anniversary, 1993 (Box 9)
      - Fortieth Anniversary
        - Celebration Book, 2003 (Box 9)